Sahaja yogis should not fall to such a level
of mundane type of people after all what is going to happen to you
I would say those who have been worrying and all that,
should go into great meditation and understand
that you are insulting yourself. You are saints;
why should you worry about what plane you are going to get,
what you are not going to get? Shows that your level is very low;
definitely; all those who have worried.
You have come here under My protection,
and you will go back under My protection.
I got so sick this morning that I was thinking we’ll not have any poojas.
You must know that you are all part and parcel of My being;
I have put you in My body and you have to behave yourself.
on such an auspicious day, when we have all come here
to do this special pooja, and I would say this should be called
as a Mahalakshmi Pooja because it’s something to do
with the industry of this country, and of the whole world.
Unless and until all those human ventures are connected with God
they cannot get their perfect stage and their status.
That’s why we have problems now in the West.
Supposed to be very clever people, very smart,
very well equipped, well educated. We are having recessions
and things because they have no balance.
They don’t know that there is God’s power which works everything,
and when you neglect that, this is what happens to you.
Now for any venture that we do of this kind,
first of all we have to use a lot of material from the Mother Earth,
but if it is taken for a proper purpose, for constructive things
and for helping others, with a balance,
then Mother Earth can think, She can produce, more and more,
all this She has produced before.
She can produce for people who are sensible,
who are in tune with God, not just making money for themselves,
or for their own purpose, but are thinking in totality,
thinking as to what we can achieve by doing this.
And that is how an industry can grow.
Now we see in Japan so much industry has grown,
but no spirituality. They are not at all happy people.
Their children are suffering, families are suffering.
Money cannot get the total well being of a human being.
So a balance has to be drawn.
Especially in our country, thank God, we didn’t have
such a fast industrialization, and that’s why we are saved
of lots of problems that the Western people are suffering,
about which the Indians are not aware.
They think you are all living in a very comfortable life there.
Industry has to go hand-in-hand with the handicrafts,
and the industrialists have to also look after the artists,
because otherwise who will look after them?
How will they bring forth the balance between the art and the industry?
And art is such a soothing thing for these hard-working people.
They work the whole day, then there is some sort of a music,
art, to console them, to give them peace, to relax them,
and a balance. So I would say that all industries
must take to some artistic ventures also, or they should also produce things.
After I was telling Rajesh many a times that you should try to produce
something artistic out of the steel scrap that is left over, will be a good idea.
They have tried something like that.
But industry should not be looked down upon
as it is looked down upon in our country.
I mean, as if industrialists are the greatest thieves
and all the politicians are saints in this country. It’s the other way around I think.
It should be treated with respect,
and should be understood that it’s very important.
And the industrialists, if they become also enlightened,
they can do a lot, not only to their own country,
but also to the people whom they are looking after.
So in the Mahalakshmi principle,
Mahalakshmi has various mudras [postures].
One of the mudra is that She puts Her right hand like this.
Now this right hand is to give protection to people
who are under the protection, or under the service,
of some rich man, or the industrialist we can call it.
In India if you call somebody a rich man it’s like abusing him.
Nobody likes it, because the rich are always shown
to be the worst people, which is not so.
In My own experience it’s not so. If there’s a poor man also he could be terrible.
We have had very bad experiences now, in Ganapatipule,
of very poor people how they behaved
in a very funny manner - supposed to be poor.
So it should be a proper balance, it should be brought to a proper balance,
between the understanding of the poor and the rich, and the rich and the poor.
After some time you will find that people will not consider poverty
or riches as so important, but the richness of the spirit
will become very important.
That is what is going to be the Sahaj nations
where the richness of the heart, the spirituality,
oneness with the Divine, will become the greatest boon
for everyone. But still we are struggling
to be on that state; many are; and still we go into materialistic tantrums
or some sort of a stupid worrying fall.
All these must be carefully watched.
If you can keep this chariot of new progress
progressing faster
we are going to create a new world of complete harmony,
complete peace, joy and love. But for that
you are the ones who have to do it. I cannot do it.
If I could have done it
I would not have asked you to join Sahaja Yoga.
It’s like the horses and the charioteer;
horses are to be driven; charioteer doesn’t drive the chariot.
In the same way you must understand your responsibility
that this is the greatest work we are doing.
It’s not only the industry, or the labor and the capital,
I’m talking about, but I’m talking about the totality of well being.
Of course all of this is a part and parcel of that, no doubt.
But the balance should be with the totality.
So we have to think of a total well being.
Once we start thinking of the total well being then –
first thing that should come to us:
Are we capable of bringing up that total well being? Are we?
Have we got the total well being within ourselves or not? Have we?
We are still worried if the plane is coming or not,
I mean, we are so mundane, so little, so small.
With one Bandhan you can control any plane, any atmosphere,
and here you are, I mean, still worried about things
which are absolutely under your control.
So this totality has to be thought over.
What is this totality that Mother is talking about?
In this totality a world has to be created of people,
by the people, who have no fear. This fear has to be given up.
Behind all this nonsensical nervousness is fear.
So for that, what She does is to give ‘अभयदान [‘Abhaydaan’—gift of fearlessness]
Under Her protection you are beyond fear, you are protected.
But if you do not want to believe in yourself,
and you don’t believe into Her protection, then no body can help you,
because everything is mythical for you.
In every venture that we take up we should not have any fear
because God is with you. Is a fact, is the truth. You just try.
But when you try through your ego you fall into the trap of fear.
I have seen egoistical people are the most frightened people,
and panicked, because they panic others
and so they think they can be panicked one day.
When the English were here, first of all, in India,
we were all frightened of them. Now I see
that in England every English family is frightened of others.
They’ll only open a chink of the door to see who is there,
and shut it. They’re so frightened. I’m surprised,
they are the same English who ruled us here.
And we were so peevish before them and now
they are the ones who are frightened of us;
because when a person who is egoistical tries to dominate others
he sees himself in the mirror and thinks
that the other person will dominate him.
That’s how this fear creeps in, into our minds,
and we start getting all kinds of these stupid tantrums
out of this mythical fear.
The fear is created by our ego.
A person who has no ego, he’ll have no fear
because he has not harmed anyone.
Why should he have any fear? And such a man, or such a woman,
will be looked after by God, because God takes over.
When you surrender your ego to God He takes over.
But those who have ego He says, “All right, go ahead,
use your ego, try to protect yourself, cut your throat.”
That’s what it is. So when I talk of total benevolence
I’m talking about your own total benevolence.
So first is the fear,
which should go out of your mind completely
if you believe in the Almighty God. We’ll say,
“You are Almighty God, you are almighty this thing”
It's all lip-service. If you believe that God is almighty,
and you are connected with God,
then why should you have any fear of anything?
But when we say, “Don’t have fear,” another extreme comes up,
“We don’t have fear, we can do what we like,
we can perform everything ourselves, we need not tell anyone.”
You have to tell God whatever you are doing.
You have to take permission, you have to inform in His darbar [court],
in His court, that, “Sir, we are thinking of doing such and such thing.”
But you think you are God. You are not.
And that’s why the another part of non-fear
is this kind of an arbitrary behavior
which is very dangerous for Sahaja Yoga,
for yourself, and for everybody else.
The second fear, I mean, I have, is that if I tell you anything,
99 percent of you understand is for your benevolence,
is for your good. But there is one [1] percent of people
who can just react because they have too much ego and they won’t take it,
because they don’t think of their own benevolence.
They don’t understand that if I am telling them anything,
it is just to give them completeness, totality.
But, on the contrary, they take a very wrong attitude;
this is another nonsensity. So now one has to develop
a kind of a indifference to this kind of people
who unnecessarily go to the other limit of their own destruction,
and don’t want to see what is the point in everything
that I am telling you. Only I can tell you. Who else?
I have to tell you what’s wrong with you,
what you have done wrong, and then you must change it.
This is another style of reaction one gets,
means they are not interested in their own benevolence,
they’re not interested in the benevolence of their children,
they’re not interested in the benevolence of their country or the whole world.
Now why have you come to Sahaja Yoga? Just ask one question.
Of course for you to ascend. But ascend for what?
Supposing we bring one tube light.
For what we have to take the tube light? But for what?
We have to put the light. But this tube light doesn’t give light,
nothing of the kind, so what’s the use of having this tube light?
In the same way, what’s the use of coming to Sahaja Yoga
if you cannot become the light of the Divine?
So all of you, each one of you, is not at all a small person;
no one; but you don’t realize what you are;
still have those funny conditionings by which you think
you are no good. All of you can come up,
and see so many people. If they take to total benevolence
within themselves it will manifest itself outside; absolutely; it’s a fact.
Then the attention is very important.
The attention should be on your own perfection
and on your total benevolence. This is also another point people miss,
that they start finding faults with others
instead of finding faults with themselves.
As a result, if you look at others, what will you get out of it?
I just don’t understand. If somebody is wrong,
he’s doing something evil, he's bad, even if you put attention to him,
what will you do about it? But if you have something wrong,
you have every right, you have every control,
and you can correct yourself. This is especially Indian quality,
is to find faults with others.
They’ll never see that what’s wrong with us.
All the time the attention is involved in finding with faults with others.
Then how can we improve? On the contrary,
if you start seeing faults, you get faulty much more.
It’s a copycat nature of human beings.
They see somebody doing like this,
“Oh Mother, he’s a Sahaja yogi, he does like this,
so what’s the harm if I do?”
But who says he’s a Sahaja yogi?
So ‘Sahaja yogi’ is not a brand, it's not a certificate,
it’s not a kind of a organization, but it is your own status
that you have achieved. Anybody can say,
“I’m a Sahaja Yogi.” After all I cannot stop him from saying.
I’m not such and such. Even I have seen some mad people,
they are Sahaja yogis, for years together they’re mad,
but they’re Sahaja yogis. But you have to see for yourself,
am I a Sahaja yogi or not? Before certifying yourself,
why don’t you find out? But despite that, I must say,
it's such a satisfaction. I never expected that so many people
will get their realization to begin with, never.
I mean, I knew that it was amass modus operandi I have developed,
but I never expected. But it has happened,
and even now I have to expect that all of you
will achieve the highest, highest positions, the paramapada [supreme state],
as I said, like the North Pole, or like the Meru; absolutely ”Atala” [firm]
‘which cannot be disturbed’. So that’s My hope,
and I’m sure you will all comply with it.
Should speak in Marathi now, as many people do not understand the English language.
It doesn't matter; there is nothing worthwhile about the English language.
There is no language like Marathi.
And again, the Marathi language is there to gain knowledge of the Soul.
And saints and sages have worked so much here; the work with the Kundalini we do is of the Natha sect itself.
But what I want to say is that although the Marathi language is at a very high level and Maharashtra has the Kundalini of the entire universe,
Maharashtrian people's minds are nevertheless upside down these days; I don't know what has caused it.
What has happened in politics has also happened in our own homes—within Sahaja Yoga.
Everyone is looking to pull each other down [pulling each other’s leg]; I don’t understand why people are doing this.
Hey, if there is no unity among you, no collectiveness among you,
then did I work hard for so many days here for this individual form of yours?
And have the saints and sages told only this?
It was told to the extent that “Those alone will be your relations.”
Hey, why did that Saint Gyaneshwara tell so much? I don't understand who this was told to.
It seems to be said for people abroad,
because it doesn't affect anyone here.
Who [are] your relations? Those Sahaja Yogis alone.
But “This person has made this mistake,” “That person has made this mistake”— and they send big-big letters to me.
Will I feel good listening to these things?
Should you be keeping the Goddess happy or should you be writing such letters to Her?
Now, every time I say that, I wonder who I'm talking to.
O you saint, sage, I made you a saint, made saint, brought you to such a high state.
You were taken to that unshakable position like a Dhruva, and now where are you lying here?
I don't understand what to call this.
Even though Marathi is such a graceful, such an intense,
and extremely good language for self-knowledge
—that should be the need of the Marathi listeners, no?
If it does not get into their heads, so then what use is it to tell?
On the other hand, people have done countless things with Kundalini.
Now, [I am] telling them in Hindi.
Marathi people should accept the truth that [their] language is a wonderful language for Self-Realization;
there is no doubt about it.
It has not been written more clearly than this in any language.
And in this regard, because people show respect to Lord Ganesha, they are of good character—as a matter of fact.
Their eyes do not roam about here and there.
In North India, because of the Muslim rule and because of their “pardah [veil]” system,
they have a custom of looking at every person who is moving around; everyone.
I used to think in the beginning, what are all these people doing?
Whatever it is, now, after coming to Sahaja Yoga.
In the Marathi language, on Self-Realization, many scriptures and many things have been written—amazing.
The one effect of these writings on these people has been that they are not womanizers.
They don’t get trapped in this, so much in Maharashtra.
There are some who got involved with women; they all have gone now and are sitting in Delhi.
But whoever is here has one specialty within them, and that is their good character.
And in North India, I was amazed to see that even among those who had never heard of Dattatreya,
how there was such awareness?
There was no sign of conflict or trouble anywhere.
The program went on so well that everyone was astonished.
If I have to say in Marathi, when people from abroad arrive here, the main focus is on how to extract money from them.
It is not like this there [North India].
And by doing all this, they have shown that, in whichever trough [pitiable condition] they were lying,
they have risen from that absolutely and become like lotuses.
This they have shown.
Now in Maharashtra, because all these things are there and everything has been written,
the saints and sages worked so hard here.
so,where there is so much effort,
I think that is where things go wrong.
Everything is known to them.
Even after knowing everything, they have muddled everything.
So, it is better that don’t have to know anything;
just realize one thing that “mutual love” is the biggest and prime mantra of Sahaja Yoga.
Then a lot of work will be done.
Otherwise, hear mantra after mantra from them; hear everything.
They know everything in the world, but the moment they see each other, they start swearing.
Now, by experience, it has been proven that in North India, it is an amazing thing the way people have accepted Sahaja Yoga.
amazing thing, very amazing. In my opinion, if this happens in Maharashtra also, then what more do I want?
In this small part of India, wonder how many saints and sages have taken birth.
And those saints and sages have been recognized by all the people of India.
They have written such valuable phrases, which are worth reading.
And their majesty cannot be described at all.
Now, that element is deeply ingrained and woven into the local culture.
But they are not able to get into Sahaja Yoga.
There is one thing in Sahaja Yoga: the culture of Sahaja Yoga should be accepted
—the greatest thing in the culture of Sahaja Yoga is mutual love.
If we don’t feel love for one another, then we are not Sahaja Yogis.
As long as one Sahaj Yogi cannot express his love for the other, we cannot become Yogis at all.
If we are busy cutting each other’s throats, then we cannot be Sahaja Yogi in any way.
You need not see others’ drawbacks.
See his virtues and describe his goodness, and he also will become a good.
I do it many times.
If someone comes and tells me that this person is like this, he did this wrong, he did this.
“Arrey! He was appreciating you, and you are talking ill of him?”
“Is that so? What did he say mother?”
“He said so many things about you.
What can I say? You go and check with him.”
Then this person goes and hugs him. It means this is all a lie.
Now, reflect deeply on the times into which we were born.
We are born in an era when a great significant task is unfolding.
Very big. Regarding this, it has been mentioned that this important work will happen.
When we are born at the time when this great work is happening,
and we are active in that, and we are the doer of this work,
when the burden of doing that work is on us, then what should we do?
If four people are carrying a table and even one among them is weak,
then the table will fall down.
Or, in a ship, even if there is a small hole, the whole ship may drown.
Because all these matters are collective.
Because you all are collective.
If among you even a single person takes the wrong path,
the whole Sahaja Yoga is harmed by it.
So, in this, we have to understand that there should be humility among us.
Jesus Christ has told that “Meek in heart will inherit earth”.
Among Maharashtrians, this humility is lacking.
Somehow, in-spite-of their language being so beautiful,
while talking, though there is no abuse in the language,
still without using abusive language, they will give some or the other lesson.
[This] is one of their characters.
This was not there before.
Earlier, it was not there; now it is there.
And they are so obsessed with this that they are ready to fight everywhere.
[They] would do strike everywhere, would do this and do that everywhere.
Don’t understand anything.
Temperament has become that of a fighter.
Human being should pay attention to this fighting temperament because now we have come in Sahaja Yoga;
we have worn its garlanded. Now leave all this.
But they won’t listen. If you tell them to become “Warakari” [Pilgrims of Lord Vitthala*],
would go on a pilgrimage for a month—chewing tobacco, wearing the robe [clothes in tattered condition], starving themselves, thousands of them.
But if they are told that they have become Sahaja Yogis, so impersonate that,
then it is a very difficult task.
So, the most important thing—the supreme element in ‘Sahaj Dharma’—is absolute mutual love; absolute.
Now look—a Muslim boy from Algeria said to his parents,
"Where are you going, dear? To Mecca?"
Nowadays, Mecca is stationed in London; go there.
He brought them to London. So, when they met me,
they said afterward, “It is true, whatever we don’t get in Mecca, we got here.”
And they said, “Just the thought that we went to London brings waves of joy in our heart.”
Just like this, just the thought of any Sahaja Yogi should bring flow of joy.
He had remained such Sahaja Yogi.
[It] is in Marathi; I have often cited this example—and I will share it again
—of the time Namadev decided to meet Gora Kumbhar and went and stood there.
Gora Kumbhar was busy trampling the clay.
After he stood there—simply “Thakale” [showed his sudden encounter].
In Hindi there is no translation but thakale.
And what did he say? "I have come to meet the formless (nirguna) with the manifest (saguna)."
This is the identity of a Sahaja Yogi.
I’ll tell you in English. I have told you many a times
about Namadeva and Gorakumbhar, how Gorakumbhar,
when he saw Namadeva, Namadeva saw Gorakumbhar
was kneading the clay for his pottery, pottery.
he just went and stood before him stunned.
And what he says that, “I have come to see here the formless”
that’s the vibrations. “But the Formless is in a form”
This is the appreciation one should have,
one Sahaja yogi should have for another.
Every Sahaja yogi is a gem.
Even the thought of a gem should bring joy to you.
In every life, every style, in every areas, every dimensions,
one should have this kind of a feeling. Muslims, Hindus, Christians,
we do not accept. For us we are all Sahaja yogis,
and we have faith in all the religions, not the 'samabhaava' [to consider everyone as equal].
We have faith in every thing. As well as we worship Rama
we worship Muhammad Saahaab also, same way, no less.
As we worship Brahmadeva, or as we worship,
we say, Dattatreya, we worship Zoroaster, there’s no difference at all,
same way. There’s a big difference in having just a same,
what you call, the same respect; it’s not that;
but we worship the same way, so there’s no question
of differentiating each other; nor on country-wise, nothing.
And whatever defects we have, we see to it
that this has come from our country;
which I see many Sahaja yogis tell Me, “This is typical English,
this is typically French, this is typically Italian.”
They themselves tell Me. But main thing one has to understand is this,
that in Sahaja Yoga we have lost all these boundaries; nothing is there.
We have reached that state where we are all one.
And the idea of any Sahaja yogi whatsoever,
and any individual Sahaja yogi, or a group of Sahaja yogis,
should fill you up with joy and a kind of a wave of joy
which is continuously coming, because they are in the form of joy,
peace. If this appreciation is reached, then only one can say
that you are Sahaja yogis, and that is one of the tests I have seen.
You love Me very much I know, all of you,
but unless and until you love each other how am I going to be happy?
So today specially, this Mahalakshmi principle,
when it is awakened within you, then you get out of a Lakshmi principle,
which makes you a little selfish maybe, self-centered,
and you get into a new dimension of searching,
of searching the higher value system, something beyond,
without any limitations. And that Mahalakshmi principle
is really nothing, in essence, if you see, is nothing but you are seeking the universal love,
in the essence it is that. We don’t love people
because they belong to some country, because they look like this,
that this is this; nothing; we love them
only because they are our part and parcel, we are one with them.
So those who are today worshipping Mahalakshmi should feel
how many worshippers of Mahalakshmi are there,
and they are all our own. It’s such a great feeling.
Otherwise, in Maharashtra especially, I must say, it was horrible,
one Sahaja yogi goes to preach in another Sahaj, another district.
(Background noise) The district leader starts fighting, just like this sound,
“Who are you to come here? I’m the leader”
Instead of respecting him, and making him a welcome guest,
asking him what can you help, there’s a big fight.
It’s really surprising. How can it happen?
When Namadeva went to Punjab, Guru Nanak Saahaab respected him;
not only that, but he told him that,
“You write now in Punjabi language also.”
I have seen such a big book written by Namadeva. Can you imagine?
He included all the great saints of Maharashtra in his Granth Saaheb,
because he knew that these are realized souls, they are higher souls.
But these Sikhs are only reading it; nothing goes into their heads.
What can you do? So at that time,
if these saints could love each other,
could express themselves in such a manner, why not we,
the Sahaja yogis from all over the world?
So I would say now, that, let us see, it’s a very nice program of Raas [folk dance linked to Lord Krishna & Gopis]
we’ll be having, where all the Indian and foreign Sahaja yogis are going to be together,
and are going to dance together. All such things are there.
So don’t sit in groups, but mix up with others, know them,
and this is what we are going to know;
each and every Sahaja yogi of the whole world.
Is very important for Me that you should love each other.
It will really soothe Me the most, it will give Me the greatest joy,
the greatest achievement, and the fulfillment of My life.
If somebody is really, definitely wrong, you just write to Me
and I will know, because immediately I’ll know from vibrations.
Nobody can befool Me, that’s one thing for sure.
Some people say that, “Somebody has told this to Mother."
Nothing can be told to Mother, you don’t know;
I am too cunning for all this. Nobody can tell Me anything;
I know each and every... I play around a little bit,
but I know each and every person. I give them a chance
to hang themselves for a time being.
But never believe that anybody can befool Me, and tell anything.
I listen to everyone, and you can try that.
If you love another Sahaja yogi,
this loving process itself is so joy giving.
When you first saw Me this time on the stage, you felt that way,
because this process of loving is the greatest joy-giving thing.
So be happy, be joyous. If some people are missing the plane,
well and good, you will live with other Sahaja yogis,
you are after all, you are somewhere in the world, you are not lost.
Even if you are in the sea, you are there, on the plane you are there.
What does it matter? Why is it so important
that this plane must be reserved, and you must worry about this plane,
“I must get out at this time” There’s no need.
Wherever you are you are with Sahaja yogis,
so why worry?
You are, that’s the point. Like many people ask Me,
“Mother You travel so much, how is it You don’t get tired?”
Because I never think I am travelling, I just think, “I am,”
that’s all. Whether in the plane or here, or there,
I am just there. I have to tell Me I am traveling,
then again I forget. So you are,
whether you are here or in England, or anywhere,
or you are here or you are there. So why to worry?
Specially with the plane - I think there is something wrong
with the Western genetics - the plane enters into their Kundalini,
I think, and they go so bizarre with the airplanes.
Something I’ve never been able to understand it.
I’ve given them so many lessons to show that don’t do all this nonsense,
but still they go on doing like this.
But if I tell them they feel guilty,but again they do it.
Next time if your plane is eight o’clock,
go at nine o’clock, the plane will wait for you till ten o’clock,
take it from Me. It has happened; so many can tell this.
So many experiences are there. I mean, we haven’t written them down,
but people know how planes have been delayed for us.
I have never missed a plane all My life, and when I missed it,
it was with a purpose; these big things happened.
So it is important, it’s a drama.
The worry should be one:
“Why can’t I love everyone as I love myself?”
I tell you only this universal love will give you
that confidence and that higher status.
Why these saints suffered for you?
Why did Christ suffer for you?
Why Muhammad Saahaab suffered for you?
Why anybody talked to you about Dharma?
Why Gnaneshwara wrote Gnaneshwari? Why?
What did they get?
This satisfaction of their expression of universal love.
All the great poets, William Blake or anyone,
whatever they have done, it’s just
because they have this universal love and they want to express it.
Why not you do it?
So if you want your Mahalakshmi principle
to be all the time burning, then please
see that you love each and every Sahaja yogi.
That’s the message today. I hope you’ll understand that.
May God bless you.